Finding aid to the Anne MacKay papers SSC.MS.00472
Sophia Smith Collection
Anne MacKay papers
1910-2013
Sophia Smith Collection
MacKay, Anne
SSC.MS.00472
14.667 linear feet (17 boxes and 1 folder)
The collection contains personal and business files of Anne Mackay, an amateur theatre director, playwright, and author, who was prominent in the New York lesbian community in the 20th century. It includes materials regarding MacKay's amateur theater work, as well as her work as an author of fiction, nonfiction and poetry. Also well-documented is her active participation in reunion activities at her alma mater Vassar College (Class of 1949).
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was gifted by Anne MacKay between 1998 to 2012.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into six series.
Series:
Personal
Education
Correspondence
Writings
Theater and Music Productions
Photographs
Biographical Note
Anne MacKay was an amateur theatre director, playwright, and author, who was prominent in the lesbian community of New York in the 20th century. She was born in New York, NY on March 31, 1928 to Franklin MacKay and Isabel (Dorman) MacKay. She grew up in New York City, Corning, and Orient, NY; Pittsfield, MA; and Berkeley, CA. Summers were spent with extended family in Orient, NY, on the North Fork of Long Island. MacKay attended the Dalton School in New York, and graduated from Vassar College in 1949. From 1949 to 1953, she was stage manager for various New York theater companies, and from 1953 to 1973 she taught Drama at the Dalton School. She was employed as Director of Theatre Arts at the Horace Mann School in New York from 1973 to 1991, when she retired.
MacKay was active in the amateur theater scene, creating and directing three lesbian musical revues, including "Taking Liberties," performed at Symphony Space in New York in 1984. She also wrote poetry and several books about lesbianism and other topics, including Wolf Girls of Vassar on the experience of lesbian students at Vassar. MacKay was active in the Vassar Alumnae community, and founded the Lesbian and Gay Alumnae of Vassar College. She was also a member of a lesbian community on Long Island's North Fork and a founder of that group's women's health initiative, the North Fork Women for Women Fund, for which she also served as archivist. She died in 2012.
Related Materials
North Fork Women for Women Fund Records, Voices of Feminism Oral History Project
Scope and Contents
The collection contains the personal and professional papers of Anne MacKay, reflecting MacKay's decades of teaching theater at two prestigious NYC prep schools (Dalton and Horace Mann Schools) and her amateur theater work. The collection also includes her work as an author of both fiction, nonfiction and poetry. Particularly well documented is her active participation in reunion activities at her alma mater Vassar College (Class of 1949). Materials include books she wrote or edited, literary manuscript, scripts, photographs and scrapbooks, school work, correspondence, and audio-visual materials. Much of the collection has notes from MacKay explaining her relationship to individuals and organizations. Materials related to MacKay's work in the North Forks Women for Women Fund are in their own separate collection.
Appraisal
In 2019, approximately 3 record cartons were removed from the collection and discarded, including duplicates, blank stationary, sensitive information (third party student evaluations and financial records), and widely available Vassar materials (including scrapbooks and reunion books available at Vassar's archives).
Lesbian communities--United States--History; Lesbians--United States--Biography--Sources; MacKay, Anne. Just lucky, I guess!: memoirs of a Wolf girl, or, Growing up in sheep's clothing (1995); MacKay, Anne (ed.). Wolf girls at Vassar: lesbian and gay experiences, 1930-1990 (1992); MacKay, Anne (ed.) She Went A-Whaling: The Journal of Martha Smith Brewer Brown (1993); Typescripts; Lesbians -- United States -- Biography -- Sources; Authors, American--20th century--Biography--Sources; Books; Soares, Manuela; MacKay, Anne; Vassar College--Students--History; Soares, Manuela; MacKay, Anne
- Personal, 1928-2007; 1
  Scope and Contents
  The series includes photographs and materials pertaining to MacKay's childhood, personal correspondence, memorabilia and planning for MacKay's birthday celebrations, legal records concerning her father's death, backup disks from MacKay's personal computer, personal memorabilia, and recordings of performances by MacKay and friends. Additional personal correspondence and performances can be found in the correspondence and theater series respectively.
  - Baby Book, 1928-1934 (Box 1)
  - Childhood Writings and Drawings, 1931-1941 (Box 1)
  - Isabel Dorman (mother) and Dorman Family, 1925-2006 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Father, undated (Box 1)
  - General attorney documentation, financials, and correspondene re. the estate of John J. MacKay, 1980-1988 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook for Anne's Birthday, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Gathering Committee and Women's Coffee House, 1983-1993 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence re. romantic relationships, 1945-2004 (Box 1)
  - Clyde Phillip Wachsberger Watercolor Album, 2007 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, photographs, 80th birthday plans, 2008 (Box 1)
  - 80th Birthday Book, 2008 (Box 1)
  - 80th Birthday Celebration Songs, 5 April 2008 (Box 1)
  - Obituary - Suffolk Times, 3 May 2012 (Box 1)
  - John MacKay Home Movies video recording, undated; 1 items (1 VHS)
  - MacKay dulcimer performance - cassette tapes, undated; 2 items (cassette tapes) (Box 15)
  - Sandy & Eunice, Westerly Nursing Home (cassette), 1979; 1 items (cassette tape) (Box 15)
  - Home movie: "early stuff" (VHS), undated; 1 items (VHS) (Box 14)
  - Backup (floppy disks), undated; 11 items (floppy disks) (Box 14)
  - Backup Disks (documents, etc.) (CDs), 2000-2007; 7 items (CDs) (Box 14)
  - "North Fork Crones, 1996" T-shirt (Box 12)
  - "North Fork Women's Softball + Cruising Assn." T-shirt, undated (Box 12)
  - "uncommon woman" award to Mackay, 1993 (Box 12)
  - Lavender Jane record, undated (Box 17)
  - Jean Redpath concert poster, 1986 (Box 17)
  - Laurie Faber '83 (cassette), undated; 1 items (cassette tape) (Box 15)
  - Finish of Perils & Singing in Davison and North (cassette), undated; 1 items (cassette tape) (Box 15)
  - Nancy Dean-Chaucer (cassette), undated; 1 items (cassette tape) (Box 15)
  - Emily & Nancy (cassette), undated; 1 items (cassette tape) (Box 15)
  - Reflections by Hutch, sing-along (cassette), undated; 1 items (cassette tape) (Box 15)
  - "Collette" (cassette), undated; 1 items (cassette tape) (Box 15)
  - "Take - Healey" (cassette), undated; 1 items (cassette tape) (Box 15)
- Education, 1931-2011; 2
  Arrangement
  In this series, Dalton materials and Vassar materials are seperate, and arranged chronologically.
  The series contains materials on MacKay's education at the Dalton School and Vassar College, including schoolwork, scrapbooks, yearbooks, teacher's evaluations, records of theatrical productions, school publications, and correspondence with Dalton and Vassar classmates. Also included are materials about MacKay's work as an alum of both schools, including records regarding the Lesbian and Gay Alumni of Vassar College (LAGAVC) organization, correspondence with members of the LAGAVC, records of LGBT history at Vassar, and records and correspondence concerning class reunions.
  Records of theatrical performances for Vassar reunions, such as "The Hallelujah Chorus Line", are included in "Education" rather than the "Theatre" series because they directly pertain to MacKay's experience at and involvement with Vassar College. Correspondence pertaining directly to Dalton or Vassar, including correspondence from former classmates, is included in "Education" rather than "Correspondence". This series contains only material pertaining to MacKay's own education; records of her time as a theatre teacher at the Dalton and Horace Mann Schools are included in "Theatre".
  - Transcription of Tape re. Dalton Experience, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Dalton Yearbook, 1942 (Box 1)
  - Dalton Yearbook, 1945 (Box 1)
  - Dalton Schoolwork, 1940s (Box 1)
  - Dalton Schoolwork, 1945 (Box 1)
  - Drawings & Paintings, 1940s (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous High School Documents, 1940s (Box 1)
  - Writings by Dalton Class of 1945, 1940s (Box 1)
  - Blue Flag, 1945 (Box 1)
  - Dalton Teacher Reports, 1937-1945 (Box 1)
  - The Dalton Bulletin, May 1956 (Box 1)
  - Dalton Christmas Pageant, 1992-1993 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with and re. Red Howell, 1992-2005 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Dalton classmates, 1990s (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Dalton classmates, 1998-2007 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and Memories of Dalton, 2011 (Box 1)
  - News Clippings and Writings re. Dalton classmates, 1940-1990 (Box 1)
  - Reflections on Dalton and News about Former Classmates, 2009 (Box 1)
  - "Connections", Dalton publication, 2005-2009 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence concerning Dalton GLASS (LGBT organization), 2004-2007 (Box 2)
  - Clippings and Correspondence re. Homophobia at Dalton, 1998-2002 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Dalton papers, undated (Box 2)
  - Dalton 50th Reunion, 1990s (Box 2)
  - Dalton School 60th Anniversary "Book of Memories", 1979 (Box 2)
  - Dalton Scrapbook, 1940-1945 (Box 16)
  - Dalton School Alumnae, 2004 (Box 2)
  - "Education on the Dalton Plan" by Helen Parkhurst, "The Dalton School" by Susan F. Semel, 1922, 1992 (Box 2)
  - Vassar Government Association, 1948-1949 (Box 2)
  - Schoolwork, 1947-1948 (Box 2)
  - Schoolwork for DR220 at Vassar College, 1946 (Box 2)
  - Schoolwork for English 105 at Vassar College, c. 1946 (Box 2)
  - Junior Party "Reader's Diatribe", undated (Box 2)
  - "The Spiral Weekend" programs and undated photographs, 1948 (Box 9)
  - "The Spiral Weekend" scripts, photographs, commentary, 1948 (Box 9)
  - Vassar newspapers, 1944-1950 (Box 2)
  - Photographs and Vassar-related cartoons, undated (Box 2)
  - Vassar Songbooks, undated (Box 2)
  - "The Unofficial College Songbook", undated (Box 2)
  - "Memories of a Child of Vassar by Cornelia M. Raymond, "More Light on Early Days at Vassar" by Nancy Nichols Barker, 1940 (Box 2)
  - Homosexuality at Vassar, 1970-1990 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Vassar materials, 1948-2004 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous communication with Vassar classmates, 1988-2003 (Box 2)
  - Vassar Quarterly, Winter 1990 (Box 2)
  - Vassar correspondence, 1996-2004 (Box 2)
  - Vassar Voices, 2011 (Box 2)
  - A retrospective for the Sesquicentennial, the Miscellany News, 2011 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence with Lydia Murdoch, 2011-2012 (Box 2)
  - Lesbian and Gay Alumni at Vassar College general correspondence, April-Sep. 2011 (Box 2)
  - General correspondence and documentation re. "Smashing History: 150 Years of LGBTIQA Vassar" Conference, 2011 (Box 2)
  - LAGAVC correspondence re. MacKay's April 13, 2011 Lecture at VC, May-July 2011 (Box 2)
  - Letter to Vassar Class of '49 and responses following reunion, 1974 (Box 3)
  - Scripts for 1981 Vassar reunion show (Box 3)
  - Correspondence re. Vassar 40th reunion, copies of musical script "Daisy Chain', 1988 (Box 3)
  - Songs from 40th Vassar reunion, 1988 (Box 3)
  - Vassar mini-reunion, 1997 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence re. Vassar 50th reunion, 1999 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous re. Vassar 50th reunion, 1999 (Box 3)
  - "A Hallelujah Chorus Line" 50th anniversary, 4 June 1999 (Box 3)
  - "A Hallelujah Chorus Line" 50th reunion production, 1999 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence re. "The Hallelujah Chorus Line", 1999 (Box 19)
  - "The Hallelujah Chorus Line" photographs, 1999 (Box 19)
  - "Hallelujah Chorus Line" scripts, 1999 (Box 19)
  - Vassar Songbook, 1989 (Box 19)
  - Boston mini-reunion, 1989 (Box 19)
  - "The Daisy Line" scripts, 1988-06-04 (Box 19)
  - Vassar Quarterly, 1999 (Box 19)
  - Debby Goltz folder (Box 19)
  - Transcription of a Tape made 8/30/97 for Vassar Library, Memories of Theatre at Vassar, 1999 (Box 3)
  - Vassar 60th Reunion, 2009 (Box 3)
  - Vassar 60th Reunion - correspondence and songbook, 2009 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence re. Vassar and Dalton, 2012 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, clippings, and records re. Vassar College and the LAGAVC, 1970-1990 (Box 3)
  - LAGAVC General and Bylaws, 1946-2002 (Box 3)
  - LAGAVC Newsletters, 1991-2004 (Box 3)
  - LAGAVC Library Project, 1991-2000 (Box 3)
  - LAGAVC general correspondence, 1992-2006 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence re. Alumnae House and "Wolf Girls at Vassar", 1992 (Box 3)
  - LAGAVC correspondence and forms, 1993-1996 (Box 3)
  - Feminist and Lesbian Alumnae of Smith College correspondence, Vassar alumni outreach, c. 1994 (Box 3)
  - LAGAVC - Ruth Rouff, 1994-1997 (Box 3)
  - LAGAVC treasury account, 1995 (Box 3)
  - LAGAVC - AIDS, 1996 (Box 3)
  - LAGAVC conference, 12-14 April 1996 (Box 3)
  - LAGAVC-related, 1996-1998 (Box 3)
  - LAGAVC - John Schoonbeck, 1996-2005 (Box 3)
  - LAGAVC - Lenore Kukle, 1996-2002 (Box 3)
  - LAGAVC - Jill Oppenheim, 1996-2004 (Box 3)
  - LAGAVC - Carolyn Belle Lyday '72, 1997 (Box 3)
  - LAGAVC history - Kebba, Buckley, 1998 (Box 3)
  - LAGAVC - Jan Freeman, 1998-2000 (Box 3)
  - LAGAVC - Afia Walking Tree, 1998 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence re. the LAGAVC, 1998-1999 (Box 3)
  - LAGAVC - correspondence with Jane Bishop '72, 1999 (Box 3)
  - Lesbian, Gay, and Bisexual Authors of Vassar College, 1992 (Box 3)
  - LAGAVC - Pamphlets, news articles, postcards, posters, 1997-1998 (Box 3)
  - Clippings and correspondence re. LAGAVC, 1990-1991 (Box 3)
  - LGBT Vassar History, 2001-2011 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook from Vassar, 1946 (Box 17)
  - "Coming Home" lecture poster, 2011 (Box 17)
  - Vassar theatre collage, 1947-1948 (Folder 18)
  - The Well of Loneliness (cassette tape), 1982; 1 items (Cassette tape) (Box 15)
  - Dalton Christmas Pageant (video), 1960; 1 items (DVD) (Box 15)
  - Dalton Christmas Pageant (recording), 1960; 1 items (CD) (Box 15)
  - Go Forth Unafraid: Celebrating Dalton's 85th Birthday (video), undated; 1 items (DVD) (Box 15)
  - Dalton's 90th: A Tiger's Tale (video), undated; 1 items (DVD) (Box 15)
  - Dalton Christmas Pageant, 1960; 1 items (cassette tape) (Box 15)
  - Vassar 50th reunion cassette tapes, 1999; 4 items (cassette tape) (Box 15)
  - LAGA Weekend at Vassar College (VHS), 1992; 3 items (3 VHS) (Box 14)
  - Dalton Reunion (JPG images), 2005; 1 items (CD-R) (Box 14)
  - "The Hallelujah Chorus Line!: A 50th Reunion Production" (CD), 1999; 1 items (CD) (Box 14)
  - "Coming Home", Vassar College (CD), 2011-04-13; 1 items (CD) (Box 14)
  - Vassar conference - "Smashing History: 150 Years of LGBTIQA Vassar" (CD), 2011-04; 6 items (CDs) (Box 14)
  - The Vassar Faculty (DVD-R), 1865-2011, 1 items (DVD-R) (Box 14)
  - "She Goes to Vassar" (DVD-R), 1931; 1 items (DVD-R) (Box 14)
  - "A Vassar Notebook" (DVD-R), 1970; 1 items (DVD-R) (Box 14)
  - Vassar College Women's Studies gift to Mackay for 'Distinguished Achievement in Recoering Gay and Lesbian History at VC", 2011 (Box 12)
  - "Dalton School and Grand Reunion" glass apple, undated (Box 12)
- Correspondence, 1930-2012; 3
  The series contains MacKay's correspondence with friends, family, former students, and associates.
  - Correspondence - Cynthia Beer, undated (Box 4)
  - "Medusa" Yew Wood Sculpture - Christina Biaggi, NY, 1980 (Box 4)
  - Letters & Cards to Aunt Ethel, undated (Box 4)
  - Correspondence - Louisa Castner, 2007 (Box 4)
  - Jean Redpath, 1998-2004 (Box 4)
  - Elizabeth Seeger - interview transcription, correspondence, clippings, 1973-1990 (Box 4)
  - Peggy Seeger, 1994-2003 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence from Richard Welch to MacKay, June 27, 1994 (Box 4)
  - Marian Seldes & Helen Frankenthaler, 1999-2004 (Box 4)
  - From Marion Sebles and Anne Tolstoi, 1944-1945 (Box 4)
  - From Jeff Williamson and others, college & later, undated (Box 4)
  - Loosee, 1971-1972 (Box 4)
  - From Anne to Family (saved by her father), 1935-1949 (Box 4)
  - College, 1946-1950 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with Archives, 2009 (Box 4)
  - Lesbian Herstory Archives Project & Lesbian Herstory Educational Foundation, 1989-1993 (Box 4)
  - Letters from Students, 1996-2008 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence from Past Students, 1995-2004 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence and Party Invitations, 1968-1995 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence and Writing, 1930-1940 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1942-2001 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1985-2007 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence (continued), 2007-2012 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 6)
  - Personal correspondence, undated (Box 6)
  - Correspondence from Anne, undated (Box 6)
  - Collected poems, cards, and letters, undated (Box 6)
  - Correspondence (continued) - Special Letters, c. 1970 (Box 6)
- Writings, 1921-2010; 4
  The series includes unpublished and notated drafts of MacKay's poetry; royalties agreements and bookstore orders re. "Wolf Girls at Vassar"; first and second editions of "Wolf Girls at Vassar" and "She Went A-Whaling"; unpublished manuscripts of MacKay's memoir "Just Lucky, I Guess"; unpublished science fiction manuscripts; literary journals containing MacKay's writing; collections of poetry; transcription of "Sandy Dee" oral history; correspondence, publicity, and newspaper clippings re. MacKay's writing; and recordings of a poetry reading and a talk re. "Wolf Girls at Vassar".
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  - Collected poems, cards, and letters, undated (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous Poetry, 1921-2007 (Box 6)
  - Unpublished Poetry and Drafts, 1933-2010 (Box 6)
  - Poems and Writing, 1943-1970 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous Poetry and Writing, 1946-1960 (Box 6)
  - Poetry, 2002-2009 (Box 6)
  - Poems with Notes, 2000-2003 (Box 6)
  - Poetry Drafts, 1999-2008 (Box 6)
  - Poetry Process, 2002-2010 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous Writing-related, 2009 (Box 6)
  - Sources for Poems, 1995-2005 (Box 6)
  - Writing by Others, 2000-2009 (Box 6)
  - Poetry readings, 2005-2010 (Box 7)
  - St. Martin's press contract and royalties agreement, 1992-1998 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence re. poems and stories, 1998-2004 (Box 7)
  - Publication, 2001-2005 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence re. poetry, 2004-2009 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence re. poetry, 2006-2010 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence re. 'Sinister Wisdom' journal, 2010 (Box 7)
  - "Wolf Girls at Vassar", first edition, 1992 (Box 7)
  - "Wolf Girls at Vassar", second edition with foreward by Lillian Faderman, 1993 (Box 7)
  - "Wolf Girls" bookstore orders, 1992-1993 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, articles, and clippings related to the LGBT experience America, 1970-1999 (Box 7)
  - "Wolf Girls" clippings, articles re Lesbianism at women's colleges, 1970-1999 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence re "Wolf Girls", 1999 (Box 7)
  - "She Went-a-Whaling", 1993 (Box 7)
  - "She Went-a-Whaling", transcribed and edited by Mackay, 1993 (Box 7)
  - General correspondence and records re "She Went-a Whaling", 1993-1995 (Box 7)
  - "Just Lucky, I Guess!", typed manuscript, copy 1, 1995 (Box 7)
  - "Just Lucky, I Guess!", typed manuscript, copy 2 with afterward, 1996 (Box 7)
  - "Just Lucky, I Guess!", manuscript, 1996 (Box 7)
  - Manuscripts: "Just Lucky, I Guess!", "Two Stories Writing at Vassar", "Sailing", undated (Box 7)
  - "Just Lucky, I Guess," Memoir, 1995 (Box 7)
  - "Just Lucky, I Guess," photographs, 1910-1999 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence re memoir, 1995-1997 (Box 7)
  - Science fiction, structure, timelines, and covers, undated (Box 7)
  - "The Song of the Skye", 1997 (Box 8)
  - "Reunion on World's End", undated (Box 8)
  - "The Mission on Laureu-5", 1997 (Box 8)
  - "The Mission of Laureu-5" drafts, 1997 (Box 8)
  - "Roulan Dhu" draft, 1998 (Box 8)
  - "Roulan Dhu" draft, undated (Box 8)
  - "Roulan Dhu", 1998 (Box 8)
  - "Heroes", 1999 (Box 8)
  - "The Golden Ship", 2000 (Box 8)
  - "The Lady of Coreth", 2000 (Box 8)
  - "Darin", short version, undated (Box 8)
  - "Darin", logn version, undated (Box 8)
  - "Mountain of Souls", 2002 (Box 8)
  - "Farside", undated (Box 8)
  - Harrington Lesbian Fiction Quarterly vol. 3 no. 2, 2002 (Box 8)
  - Affilia Journal of Women and Social Work vol.1 no.17, 2002 (Box 8)
  - Prairie Schooner vol.77 no.3, 2003 (Box 8)
  - "Friends" short poems collection, 2003-2008 (Box 8)
  - Poetry collections: "Friends," 2003-2004; "Gifts", 2007' "The Perfect Round", 2003-2007 (Box 8)
  - Sinister Wisdom vol. 81, 2010 (Box 9)
  - "Sailing the Edge", 2003 (Box 9)
  - Copy of "Field Notes of a Lesbian Naturalist", 2003-2010 (Box 9)
  - "Field Notes of a Lesbian Naturalist", 2009 (Box 9)
  - "Just For Us", lesbian poetry reading, 2007-10-17 (Box 9)
  - "Sandy Dee", an oral history transcribed and edited by Mackay, undated (Box 9)
  - Newspaper article re. "She Went A-Whaling", 1993-09-01 (Box 17)
  - "She Went A-Whaling" cover, undated (Box 17)
  - "She Went A-Whaling" book party poster, 1993-09-05 (Box 17)
  - Anne's Poetry Reading - Poquatuck Hall (VHS), 2007-11-17; 1 items (VHS) (Box 14)
  - Wolf Girls at Vassar cassette tapes, 1992-1993; 3 items (cassette tapes) (Box 15)
- Theatre, 1943-2012; 5
  The series includes equity agreements; songbooks, chord sheets, and sheet music; publicity, memorabilia, reviews, records, correspondence, pictures, and recordings re. productions directed by MacKay, including "Midsummer Revels" (1982), "Cruise" (1983), "Taking Liberties" (1984); material re. MacKay's time as a theatre teacher at the Dalton School and the Horace Mann School, including recordings, programs, and photographs; and recordings and records re. theatre performances MacKay supported but was not directly involved with.
  School theatre included in this series relates to MacKay's professional life; her involvement in theatre as a student and alum are included in "Education".
  - Equity, 1950 (Box 9)
  - AV guides, 1973 (Box 9)
  - ES School, 1973 (Box 9)
  - Theatre programs or info, undated (Box 9)
  - "Marine Band" music teaching sheets, undated (Box 9)
  - Songs, 1944-1949 (Box 9)
  - Sea Shanties, 2011 (Box 9)
  - Midsummer Review, 1982 (Box 9)
  - "Midsummer Revels" 1982 bulletin and "Under Milkwood" poster, undated (Box 9)
  - Die Quelle Der Loneliness Opera, 1982-1983 (Box 9)
  - Theatre photographs, 1954 (Box 9)
  - Early Professional Activities, undated (Box 9)
  - "Cruise", 1983 (Box 9)
  - DVD "Taking Liberties", correspondence with Cassidy Holliger, Drama Dept., Mini Reunion, 1984-2010 (Box 9)
  - "Taking Liberties" publicity, 1984 (Box 9)
  - "Taking Liberties" script changes, 1984 (Box 9)
  - "Taking Liberties", 1984 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence re. "Taking Liberties", 1984 (Box 9)
  - "Taking Liberties" script, 1984 (Box 9)
  - Photographs and art re. "Taking Liberties", 1984 (Box 9)
  - "Taking Liberties" director's book, 1984 (Box 10)
  - "Taking Liberties" photo album, 1984 (Box 10)
  - "Taking Liberties" microfilm slides, 1984 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous songs, undated (Box 10)
  - Ballads and carols, undated (Box 10)
  - Recent Songs, undated (Box 10)
  - Sea songs, "About Sea Shanties", 2011-02-12 (Box 10)
  - Song swap, 2011-04-16 (Box 10)
  - Songs (English), undated (Box 10)
  - Ballads, undated (Box 10)
  - Clippings, "SPAT Oyster Gardener Turns 60 Eating Birthday Oysters", undated (Box 10)
  - Untitled songs, undated (Box 10)
  - OCA meeting, 2012-03-06 (Box 10)
  - Songs and clippings, undated (Box 10)
  - General correspondences re. theatre productions, 1995-2008 (Box 10)
  - Off-Broadway Reviews, assorted newspaper clippings, 1949-1952 (Box 10)
  - Midsummer Revels - Pre-production, 1982 (Box 10)
  - Midsummer Revels - photos, undated (Box 10)
  - Midsummer Revels - audiotapes, 1982 (Box 10)
  - Oysterponds Community Activities (OCA), 2006-2008 (Box 10)
  - Greenport Friends of Film, undated (Box 10)